[Music]
good evening and good day everybody
welcome to the latest episode of the ask
a budget show episode 133
and as usual we shall discuss matters of
great import in this episode all thanks
to the questions that you ask
and before we get into that let us take
a look at who all is with us today
tonight
um
[Music]
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you thank you so much
for being with me on this
latest episode of the ask a widget show
so um i think we know what we're gonna
discuss today i think you can all guess
what uh the topics are going to be like
so without further ado
let's get into the questions
what is question number one for today
what's the question suspense okay here
we go
okay uh sorov
says with the passing away of queen
elizabeth ii
uh wanted to know if she was equally
responsible for the horrors of
colonialism imposed on india and various
african and caribbean nations since she
was born in 1926 much later after the
british occupation of india
all right a pertinent question
was queen elizabeth ii the queen of
britain and uk and all that
was she responsible for the horrors of
colonialism
so uh we can look at it in a variety of
ways let's take a look at her lineage
her family yes
uh
her great great grandmother was queen
victoria
who uh
who reigned up to 1901 i think her rule
begins in 1837 or something like that
yes and uh
she ruled over india
why are the first of all the british the
british east india company and secondly
by direct rule
for for much of the 19th century and
during this time
millions of indians were deliberately
starved to death in
a
procession of artificially induced
famines year after year after year
right millions tens of millions of
indians overall if you look at the
overall uh period of british occupation
of india more than 100 million indians
were killed in artificial famines a
significant portion of that happened
under during the rule of of queen
victoria
and victoria it's under it's during her
rule that the first war of independence
1857 happened and in the aft in the
aftermath of that at least 10 million
indians were killed in reprisals by the
british yeah so this all happened under
the watch of queen victoria queen
victoria was also responsible for the
drug running that she did i mean if you
think of the greatest drug smugglers and
drug runners in the world
you think of someone like pablo escobar
right well pablo escobar was a small fry
compared to victoria
yeah
and and
she essentially used india as a as a
base for producing opium and various
drugs which she would then sell to china
in exchange for gold and various
treasures that would be printed out of
china
the century of humiliation that the
chinese always talk about right after
victoria you had other other monarchs
essentially
so if you look at
elizabeth
her father was george vi
who ruled from 1936 to 1952 i think he
died in 1952. he presided over the
bengal famine which was the last great
artificially induced famine that the
british bestowed upon india
i would say between four to ten million
indians mostly bengalis were
needlessly and deliberately killed
during this time yeah he was also
responsible for the
partition of india and the genocide that
ensued yes
one sided genocide that ensued yes so
you could say
that elizabeth is not responsible for
this it's only her family her ancestors
that are responsible responsible for all
of these things you could say that you
could you could make the argument yeah
now if you look at various pictures of
queen elizabeth the second
you see there is crown jewels she's very
proudly wearing yes
where did these crown jewels come from
these are all stolen and plundered from
various colonies including india mostly
india where does all the wealth come
from
the british monarchs were middling
monarchs they were not great monarchs
until they acquired india india was the
jewel in the british crown
all of the wealth all of the prosperity
all of the magnificence and glory comes
from wealth plundered from india and
elizabeth may not have done it
personally but she certainly enjoyed the
fruits and the benefits of that and she
proudly displayed the stolen jewels and
she still she did that all her life and
her descendants will also do that won't
they
right so this family is is responsible
for incredible plunder incredible
amounts of misery genocide of 100 maybe
more than 100 million indians yeah
plunder slavery uk whatever you can
imagine they've done it all
she
bears the legacy she bought the legacy
of this and she wore it proudly
yes
what else so all the wealth was stolen
and plundered that's how the uk became
prosperous and rich now let's look at
the career of elizabeth ii yeah you
could argue that all of this is was best
out upon her by fate by her family and
she just took on the responsibility and
carried it forward let's take a look at
her career so elizabeth
became queen in 1952
while she was on a trip to kenya they
said that she went up a tree princess
and she came down the tree uh queen that
sort of thing because she learned that
her her daddy had passed away in
in the uk
so as soon as she became queen there was
this rebellion in kenya that took off
the mao mao rebellion which lasted about
eight nine years 1952 to about 1960 or
so
at this time winston churchill was the
prime minister of the uk he was her
prime minister
and he unleashed horrors
upon the people of kenya horrific
warfare
millions of bombs were dropped on on
kenyan civilians
horrific abuses happened
the kind of torture i cannot even utter
over here
that's what was done routinely upon the
kenyan people
under the supervision of queen elizabeth
ii
more than a million innocent kenyan
civilians men women and children were
placed in concentration camps in
horrific conditions under the
supervision
and benevolent gays of queen elizabeth
ii and mr winston churchill yes so this
happened while she was queen she was no
different
from her predecessors and her ancestors
then you had the swaze crisis 1956 in
which uh
the
british
invaded
an independent nation egypt
along with france and israel
now israel had some actual reasons for
doing it but what business did britain
have invading a sovereign nation egypt
yeah that's a whole different story i'm
not going into the story the causes and
all that but uh
and the americans had warned the british
not to go not to go and do this but they
did this anyway and this was the end
of british supremacy in the world 1956
marks the passing of the baton the
transfer of power from from london to
washington right so she under her
under her supervision
under her directions britain tried to
invade egypt yeah so the imperialism is
very much there there was no difference
in policy now let's talk about the 1971
bangladesh liberation war people don't
really really know about the role that
britain pale played in this we know that
the uss enterprise was sent by president
nixon yeah task force 71 it was sent
into the indian ocean the bay of bengal
to intermediate india apparently now
most people don't know that the british
also sent a carrier battle group an
aircraft carrier carrier battle group
the hms eagle
and its accompanying warships
to accompany the uss enterprise and that
tax force in order to intimidate and
bully india
yes this was all done
under the direct supervision of
elizabeth ii so there you go the same
mentality the same approach imperialism
bullying other nations
same thing
and in africa colonialism then let's
talk about ireland the irish occupation
the british occupation of ireland
yeah uh
i ireland northern ireland essentially
is still under british occupation it is
it is british occupied northern ireland
it is
and the people of ireland don't want
british rule even today
yeah and the kind of atrocities the
british perpetrated in ireland in
northern ireland ireland especially
during elizabeth's time
are kind of suppressed you know we don't
know about these things for instance the
1972 bloody sunday massacre in which 26
unarmed civilians
were massacred in northern ireland in
the town of derry that's just one
example
of the brutality and oppression that the
british perpetrated on their irish
neighbors and are still doing
and this all happened during
queen elizabeth ii's rule
then there is the malvinas war the
falklands war in 1982 in which there was
this
unprovoked aggression i mean you could
call it provoked or whatever
what business does britain have
occupying islands off the coast of
argentina in south america close to the
south pole what business does britain
have doing that and yet they went there
with
with their navy and they the argentines
tried to uh take over the islands and
the british beat them off this all this
is again imperialism and colonialism all
under elizabeth ii and then you
you
have the consistent support that the uk
has given to pakistan throughout
elizabeth's rule
and the uk all the newspapers all the
institutions all the policies the
foreign policy etc have been
consistently anti-india
yes
so that is
the legacy of elizabeth ii
she was no different from her
predecessors and her her ancestors and
her family she was just the same
no different
yeah
what and what about her legacy for for
the uk i mean let's even talk about that
yeah i mean uh
so she she i i think during her rule
there were 15 prime ministers in the uk
the last
great prime minister so to say of the uk
was margaret thatcher who uh was prime
minister from 1978 79 i think 79 until
1990 yeah then there was a transition
period in which you had john major who
was prime minister in the late 1990s
until the late 1990s 96 97 97 i think
then tony blair now tony blair is
universally regarded and i this is this
is not my words
yeah i'm just quoting
he is universally regarded as a
american as an american lap dog as an
american poodle so it is with the coming
of tony blair to power or or the
installation of tony blair as prime
minister that the uk became a proper
vassal state of the us this happened
during elizabeth's tenure
and then after
tony blair was was prime minister for a
decade or so he was very close to the
americans
and after uh his time was up you had a
procession of prime ministers gordon
brown david cameron teresa may boris
boris johnson and now you have a the
latest one whoever whatever her name is
liz trust right she's been around for
six or seven days as prime minister a
whole process in a procession of prime
ministers after tony blair
you can see the japan playbook being
unleashed on the uk yes japan also apart
from one great man shinzo abe they had a
procession of prime ministers who did
nothing who no one remembers the same
thing is now happening in the uk
one mediocrity after another
so that that is the legacy of elizabeth
she presided over the
crumbling of the british empire until
1956 britain was still
a world power after the swiss
misadventure they ceased to be a world
power they became a second rate power
today they are a third rate power so
elizabeth no matter how much you
eulogize her to the to the high heavens
she presided she took over
the crown she was crowned the queen
when britain was still maybe number one
number two number three in the world in
terms of great powers it was still it
still had that great prestige and today
it's not a secondary power it's a third
rate power it's former colony the
india has surpassed it in terms of now
of annual gdp and it's just the
beginning
so this is the legacy of elizabeth the
second she was no different from her
from her ancestors and her predecessors
she had the same colonialist objectives
and mindset the same imperial
behavior
nothing different
right so yeah
so if you were to ask whether she was
responsible for the horrors of
colonialism imposed about india well she
came after that but she continued the
same policies and other places she tried
her best to uh
to continue all that didn't work because
there was a new power on the horizon the
bigger daddy
so that's what happened
question number two
okay this is a very popular question
swarup says the government of india has
decided that there will be one day of
state morning on september 11th
throughout india in the wake of the
demise of elizabeth ii i don't think
she's worth mourning even for one second
as neither she nor the royal family has
given an official apology to india for
their barbaric barbaric doings your
thoughts on this
edwin stone snowden says i thought we
were going on the right track with the
navy enzyme in renaming of rajput
but now india has announced state
mourning for the death of queen
elizabeth is there any explanation for
this move that you can see imperial says
the indian government declared one day
of state morning on september 11 and so
on on the other hand the state same
government talks about removing the
colonial mindset and erasing the
colonial legacy isn't that hypocritical
so this is just three questions i've got
like i don't know 30 50 100 questions
like this yeah this these three
questions represent all of you who have
asked the
similar questions so what's the deal yes
india did declare one day of state
morning official morning september 11
and the flags will fly at half-mast and
all that what is the need for that what
is the reason for this yes
we the the prime minister on 15th of
august in his speech in his address to
the nation did say that we need to
eradicate all vestiges and traces of
colonialism in india by
by 100 years of independence 2047 yes
and we have made the right moves we
have
removed the saint george's cross from
the naval enzyme and we have replaced
that with something indigenous excellent
move and we have really renamed rajpath
to uh
karthav karma i'm not sure please
forgive me because i don't remember what
it is but we have renamed it we have
given it an indigenous name again
excellent and the place where the statue
of the british king used to stand now we
have the statue of nithya standing there
so we are making the right moves now why
did we do this why did we declare the
day of
mourning for elizabeth ii
well it's just you know it's words yeah
it doesn't make india colonized in any
way
it it still i mean kind of reminds you
of the vestiges of colonialism so the
prime minister has said that we need to
remove all traces of colonialism from
india by 2047. it's a process it's a
step-by-step process we are not there
yet
right now india is a member of the
commonwealth of nations what is the
common wealth of nations it is the
losers club it is a club of losers the
nations that were ruled by the uk yeah
the americans were also ruled by the uk
but they have chosen not to be part of
the commonwealth india because of
historical reasons because of the great
magnificent shri nehru and his
successors decided to
so because of those
leaders
leaders india is a member of the
commonwealth of nations and today
for the time being maybe it may be
something to some extent beneficial it
may serve some purpose to be in the
commonwealth for now yeah since we have
been in the commonwealth since 1947 or
whatever whenever the commonwealth was
formed uh right now we are in that and
uh
just to be polite
we have done this so this is simply a
symbolic move it may have some
geopolitical purpose see geopolitics is
not a black and white thing it's it's uh
complicated so we may not know exactly
what what the deal is the thing is it
doesn't make any difference right
the prime minister and the government
may declare one day of morning it's up
to you that you want to mourn or not
i'm not mourning anything
i'm not moaning her demise are you
mourning her demise no you're not that's
it end of story
right
so there are certain symbolic gestures
that the government does for foreign
policy reasons for diplomatic reasons
etc
it's just a gesture that we all can
ignore
what we are doing overall see these are
words words versus actions our actions
if you look at the diplomacy we are
carrying out with the uk it's quite
robust we are also eclipsing them we
have already eclipsed them
from the perspective of the economy and
so on so we are going ahead of them and
there is no stopping us so all these
small things right now india is still
not a major i mean as major a power as
we would want to be soon enough yeah so
right now let's uh let's let's uh
abide over time
hide your capabilities and bide your
time that's what ding shopping said they
are still in that phase
patience
patience my friends we will be there
and soon enough sooner rather than later
we are going to exit the commonwealth
right it's going to happen
so have a little bit of patience a
little bit of patience i mean 20 years
10 to 20 years soon enough it will
happen see the these things that take
time all right
but we are on the right track so this
state morning and all it doesn't make us
colonized anymore it's just a
token
gesture
of respect or whatever you want to call
it it means nothing it is for us
to decide whether we want to mourn her
or not and i don't think
i i know some people in india may be
like enamored with the british royal
family and orip the queen and blah blah
blah but most of us aren't right so
that's what matters
so i am not concerned about the day of
mourning it doesn't make any difference
to me and i kind of understand why these
symbolic messages and gestures are sent
out which mean nothing actually
s nayak says
please enlighten
on why the uk has a monarchy the
so-called queens and prince and king now
they're king and democracy also
is this any geopolitical strategy or any
hypocrisy on democracy
you know this is very interesting this
is a very good question by essnayak
think about it
the british
have a
royal family they have
a monarchy the king or the queen whoever
it is is the official head of state
they don't have a constitution
yes and they have a parliament
the house of lords in the house of
commons
and so on so forth and the head of state
is the
king
only the queen now the king
the british have never abolished their
monarchy
however
the puppet regime
they put in place
in india
there was a transfer of power from the
foreign occupiers
to their chosen minions in 1947. that's
what happened in 1947 it was not
independence it was uh dominion status
and then india became a republic a
couple of years later or whatever right
that's how it is so 1947 was a transfer
of power
from the british to the people they had
selected
it was selection not election there was
no democracy involved in this
and when the transfer of power happened
the people who they had selected shiri
nehru and et cetera et cetera
they
abolished the indian monarchies
so the british had already destroyed the
real royalty of india the real uh kings
and queens of india in 1857 any single
king or queen or royal family that
opposed the british in 1857 was
annihilated
and then they placed puppets in their
place
so the
royal family is supposedly continued but
these are fake royal families the real
kings and queens were killed off
annihilated and then their far-off
relatives or whatever that the traitor
relatives were put in place and in some
cases some royal families decided to
cooperate because they had no option
that way they would perhaps serve their
people in some way at least so some
royal families cooperated and some were
annihilated and replaced by puppets
that's what happened in 1857 onwards so
these are the various uh princely states
some of them actually were good people
think about the royal family of
travancore they did not allow the
british to know about the incredibly
enormous treasure
which
more than a trillion dollars worth in
today's money had the british known that
and come to know about it they would
have plundered it obviously right so
some royal families actually did
serve the nation in whatever way they
could but most were destroyed these
princely states which existed in 1947
were all well uh disenfranchised
and the the
the princely states were abolished
the royal uh uh thing was ended right
and they were given previous purses and
later on even that was ended
so india was made to abolish its
monarchical system
there had been continuings in the way
since the vedic age
yes but the british
are still continuing with their monarchy
what incredible hypocrisy this is
think about it
india was made to abolish its
monarchical system which had been in
place since the vedic days maybe the
pre-vedic days thousands of years maybe
10 000 plus years
abolished in 18 in 1947 the british are
continuing it
yeah but they are a democracy they are
first-class democracy we are supposedly
uh what some some lower form of
democracy according to the so-called
democracy rankings and all that this is
the incredible hypocrisy and we went
along with that
i am not saying this system is good or
that system is good or whatever right
but we had a system that has been
continuing for more than 10 000 years
and it was abolished by these
british appointed minions in 18 in 1947.
so uh what can i say about the fact that
the uk still has a monarchy well they do
what they want
they continue their system and they they
are proud of it we on the other hand we
we are self-loathing people we think
that everything that is indian is bad
yeah that's the problem right that's
what the prime minister spoke about when
he spoke about
colonialism we are still mentally
colonized we still feel that we are
inferior to everybody else this is the
problem please please wake up my friends
anyhow next question
what are your expectations from king
charles iii
richard says um
could you please talk about the
importance of the british queen in the
current world scenario and how is the
new british king's influence going to be
different or not so different okay let's
talk about uh shri
king charles iii
so
charles
has been the king in waiting for god
knows how long since i was a little
toddler he was a king in waiting prince
charles yes he was like waiting when
will i be king whenever when i be king
and now with the ripe old age of 73 when
he can hardly stand straight he has
become king
what are my expectations from king
charles iii he has inherited nothing
okay i'm sure he's very wealthy yeah the
british royal family i'm sure has
incredible
uh resources and reserves of wealth
plundered out from mostly india and
various other places i'm sure they are
very wealthy i'm sure they're very well
connected very powerful
but the uk which they rule is now
a third rate global power it's not even
a second rate global power
it's a complete lap dog of the u.s a
poodle
it's a vasal state
that's what it is it's totally
controlled by the united states
yeah so what has he inherited he has
inherited a vasal state
that's what he has inherited and he's so
old he can't even change anything
at the age of 73 i'm
i don't think you have the kind of
energy you had at the age of 43 yeah
kings
ideally should be young
young vigorous energetic
ambitious charles i'm sure must have
been ambitious when he was younger but
what ambition will he have at the age of
73 so i expect
i may be wrong i don't wish anybody
anything bad i expect charles to hang
around another 20 or so years like his
mother did his mother passed away at the
ripe old age of 94 i think so if charles
lives another 20 years he'll be 93 maybe
longer if he is if he is lucky
so now his son william will be the king
in waiting another 20
i don't know how many years
he's what 30 something now so he'll be
in his 50s when he eventually takes over
if everything goes well
and
their their relevance isn't much now
yeah so uh
in the current world scenario they don't
have any real importance uh various
colonized and formally colonized nations
still revere them to some extent yeah
because of the education system and the
mental colonization but apart from so
what they do is they have these periodic
tools to african nations etc nowadays
they're not so welcome to india anymore
so they typically go to african nations
and the caribbean nations and all that
and they they show how great they are
and people worship them and people
salute them people come out in large
numbers to see them and you know that
sort of thing apart from that there is
no actual geopolitical or or
international significance of this royal
family yeah it's a it's a vestige of an
older age and they are not really
relevant anymore the
custom may continue for some time for a
few more generations perhaps perhaps not
we have no idea but that's how it is so
uh
their influence is mostly zero yeah they
have no influence anymore because they
no longer are in power
they know no longer control the nation
they are just figureheads they may be
very wealthy for sure but wealth doesn't
buy you power if you have watched my
chingish khan video
you will know this
power can buy you wealth but wealth
cannot buy you power so that that's
where they are
next the question
okay siddhe says what do you think what
do you think of the new british prime
minister liz truss and how important is
the uk to india
rl says writing to you from london as
india dumps the uk behind gdp who will
benefit more from a free trade agreement
between the uk and india uk being a
major exporter of services can gain a
lot more from india access to 1.3
billion plus people then india can gain
from accessing the small and declining
uk economy how do we make sure these
looters don't try it again with india
okay okay two questions but uh
related questions what do i think of the
new british prime minister liz trust
she's a nobody
she's gonna she's gonna achieve nothing
yeah
she was one of two candidates
you know
contending vying with each other
to ascend to the post of
prime minister which is the servant in
chief of the of the u.s empire that's
all it is
she's going to achieve nothing she's
going to last maybe two or three years
and if she last too long then she will
be replaced by some other prime minister
that's how the typically works in the uk
now yeah
two three years the prime minister lasts
and then something happens you know
something is engineered political coup
or whatever and then a new prime
minister comes to place in that new
prime minister's again
a person with no great leadership
capabilities or anything no great vision
their only vision is to serve the
masters
so that's what i think of liz trust
she's a nobody and she won't achieve as
far as i um i think she you know she's
not gonna amount to anything like her
predecessors before her
her
more immediate predecessors before her
now uh the other question is about the
free trade agreement you know
the uk
is still the number six economy in the
world
the only relevance they have today the
uk in the global economy as the is as
the
global hub of money laundering
all the various
companies shell companies you know
dodgy companies shady companies etc
that exist in the world for the purpose
of money laundering they are all
headquartered in london many of them not
all many of them and there's a whole
kind of all kinds of fishy dealings
happening in london
and all the various dictators have
significant investments in the uk and in
london they own properties in the uk and
london various indian fugitives i don't
know for some reason they like to go to
london and stay there and then they they
feel very safe and comfortable there so
that's the only relevance the uk has it
says it's the global money laundering
hub
that's all it is
so uh a free trade agreement between
india and the uk i'm not sure how much
it will benefit india
and the
uk economy is declining india's economy
is gathering steam and expanding as it
should
so india won't gain much from accessing
the small small and declining uk economy
but for now we can have some kind of
deal worked out with them and what how
do we make sure these looters don't try
to get with any they are not in a
position to try anything again with
india
the uk is no longer
a world power it's not even a second
class power it's a third rate power it's
it's not in a position to try anything
with india
the only thing is they have
a significant media industry and that
still influences the
the minds of indians a lot because
indians consume news and
information in english mostly these days
and that's why they still have some kind
of uh
hold on the indian psyche that will be
dealt with in dueco in the due course of
time so that's what i think of of the uk
um
not a big deal anymore and it's gonna
become even lesser of a deal as the
years go by as it should
right now this topic here
lippon says what's your view on the usa
you the u.s has resumed imf bailout to
pakistan giving
aid and giving the clearance
to pakistan's f-16
upgradation
yasho says what are your views in the
u.s and pakistan deal up 450 million u.s
dollars for upgrading pakistani f-16
aircraft is it the consequence of russia
india oil trading when will we make our
own aircraft okay
says u.s is giving 450 million
worth of equipment for the f-16 sold to
pakistan and
should india consider american fa-18
aircraft for ins vikrant and for the
multi-role fighter aircraft programs
isn't the us playing double games with
india
weibo says the
the americans have approved this money
for the f-16 upgradation for to fight
terrorism
what's your view is the u.s again using
pakistan to hurt india yes so the
americans have announced this uh deal
this this package
450 million dollars worth of uh upgrades
to the pakistani f-16 fleet so the park
these f-16 fighter planes they date back
to the 1970s they're still a reasonably
good fighter plane here fourth
generation i think yeah and they were uh
sold to pakistan and the condition was
that it they would be used for
anti-terrorism activities
now
pakistan itself is a terrorist nation
the whole world knows this so how do you
expect terrorists to use this equipment
for anti-terrorism activities
and everybody knows
who pakistan truly wishes to target
pakistan has only one enemy which it
considers to be its mortal enemy that's
india everyone knows these f-16s will be
used in a future war if it ever happens
with india
right the target everyone knows it's
going to be india
and they use the f-16s after in the
aftermath of the balaclava uh
uh terrorist uh
the the balakot airstrikes that indeed
on pakistani terrorist camps right the
pakistanis use their f-16s against india
and now the americans
are
giving this big package to the
pakistanis almost half a billion dollars
worth to upgrade their old f-16s and
make them better
so what how do we
understand this what do we what do we
make of this see it's very clear
things can be made as complicated as you
want or as simple as you want i like to
keep things reasonably simple this is a
hostile action by the us against india
that's what it is the americans are
arming india's mortal enemy
with newer equipment they are giving
upgrades this is a hostile unfriendly
act against india there is no other way
to see this
yeah so all those who say that
you know some people in india are trying
to
you know make make a small deal of this
that that uh it's not a big thing or
anything it's a big deal
that tells you how much the americans
can be trusted
on the one hand they say that india and
the us have shared values and we believe
in democracy and we believe in freedom
and human rights and you know
uh
asia pacific strategy common power
strategy on the other hand
and they want india to they want to use
india as a bulwark as a as a
counterweight to china
and they want india to to throw their
line on the other hand they're doing
this so why have they did they done this
so there are multiple reasons first of
all india has not gone along with the
u.s line vis-a-vis the russia ukraine
situation
india has maintained an independent
foreign policy and india has not allowed
the u.s to dictate what we should do or
what we should not do yes
and we have continued purchasing oil
from the russians
they don't the americans don't like this
and now india is participating in the
vostok exercises
in the far east of russia yes so the
americans again don't like that so india
is making sending signals to the
americans that we are going to have an
independent foreign policy we are a
sovereign nation and we will not be told
what to do
in response to that the americans are
doing this
and saying look this is what we can do
to you we can once again reopen the
pakistan option
if you in case you don't remember the
americans financed more than two decades
of pakistani terrorism on india
nobody else financed it the americans
knew what was happening the americans
were financing pakistani terrorism in
india
the mumbai attacks 2008 26 11
was a consequence of that even in the
1971 war the americans tried to bully
india the americans knew what the
pakistanis were doing they were
conducting genocide in in bangladesh and
the americans were fine with this so
this is the american track record they
have never been especially pro india
they've typically been very anti india
they have used pakistan to bleed india
again and again for decades yes
and now they're again showing india that
we still have the option to do that
so what should india do about this india
should continue
having an independent foreign policy
looking out for india's national
interest
seeking a multipolar world constructing
a multi-polar world building india's
economy that's what india should do what
about the fa18 the americans have
offered the fa18 to india it's a fighter
plane
for the ins vikrant the ins vikrant will
need about 30 or 35 40
fighter planes typically it's the number
is 30 but we need some extra right so 30
35 40 or something like that we need
fighter planes so the americans have
offered their f a 18 fighter plane
should india go for it in the light of
what they are doing in the light of
their aid to pakistan
uh so that's that's something the
government needs to
take a call on
i have it or i have been of the opinion
that the rafale should be considered the
rafale won't fit into the into the lifts
the elevators of the
ins vikrant so maybe some modifications
can be done and something can be worked
out or we can
see some other option they make 29 or
something yeah
so the us is playing double games with
india in the us
the us always believes in coercive
tactics
coercive methods arm twisting bullying
and we are seeing this we're witnessing
this again yeah
uh so yes the americans are up to their
old tricks again no matter how you paint
this or portrait this is
a hostile and unfriendly action against
india
bhumika says india lodges uh yeah this
f-16 thing is done yeah
um secondly india has pulled out of the
indo-pacific economic framework group
trade pillar how is this going to impact
india u.s relations
her says bharat pulled out of has pulled
out of the ipef trade pillar is it
because of the f-16 deal that the
pakistanis and china and the americans
are going or is it because india and
china bharat relations are improving as
we have both pulled the army back
and summert says
why what is the indo-pacific economic
framework ipef
launched recently by the u.s and is it
just a waste of time why is taiwan not
part of it okay now let me share my
screen and let's take a look at what
this ipef is i'm gonna put uh
what shall i put on the screen ipef i'm
gonna put a wikipedia article on it so
once again statute rewarding wikipedia
is not always reliable in this case i'm
using it just for the sake of
convenience because i'm just showing you
the the big picture
so the ipef has i think 14 nations it's
a it's something that has been launched
in may this year may
23 this year
it's the indo-pacific economic framework
for prosperity what a wonderful name it
has and it has all these indo-pacific
nations australia brunei fiji india
indonesia japan south korea malaysia new
zealand philippines singapore thailand
us and vietnam so this essentially once
again is the u.s
the you the americans want to decouple
from china and uh
that's uh that's something that is in
progress right now so this is part of
that
so they want to pull various nations in
the indo-pacific region on the to the
american side and against china so
that's what's happening and all of these
nations are
nations that typically feel threatened
by the chinese
expanse expansionist
activities
so it makes sense for these nations to
band together and the americans are the
biggest economies so they are leading
this process yeah
so now so this ipef let's put that back
on the screen
let's put that back on the screen
so it has four pillars yeah four themes
or four pillars one is fair and
resilient trade second is second is
supply chain resilience third is
infrastructure clean energy
decarbonization whatever not whatever
that is
and the fourth is tax and
anti-corruption the main thing is
actually
trade fair and resilient trade that is
the major outcome that this entire thing
seeks because that is where the
power comes from right that's the real
deal so india has refused to become part
of that particular pillar the trade
pillar
why is this
so the
ministry of whichever concerned ministry
has put out some explanation as to why
we have done this
essentially what we are saying in
diplomatic terms is that we want to
wait until the framework matures and you
know see how it progresses and then
we'll take a call on this the actual
reason could be retaliation to the us
for their f-16 deal with pakistan it is
very much a possibility so we will not
say that that's why we are doing it but
it is to be understood that these are
this is again you know tug of war that's
happening between between india and the
americans
india is pursuing an independent foreign
policy vis-a-vis russia visa ukraine
with various donations india is pursuing
a multi-polar
world
that's the kind of world india wants and
that's the kind of game india is playing
the geopolitical game
it is a multi-alignment
not going into one person's camp the big
boys camp
yeah
in response to that in india is also
participating in the war games the
vostok war games in the far east of
russia in response to that the americans
are
they have done this deal with the
pakistanis and they are offering they
are they are selling pakistan
this big half a billion dollar worth of
upgrades through the f16
uh
fighter jet flotilla in response india
seems to have done this that we will not
be part of your of your trade pillar of
the
uh indo-pacific uh economic framework so
this is a tit-for-tat tit-for-tat
happening right now
yeah and what we we are seeing is that
the america the americans the u.s is the
only superpower in the world it is the
biggest
uh
biggest dog in the in the entire park
right india is still a much smaller
economy but india is still standing firm
and india is
telling the u.s that you cannot tell us
what to do so that's what we are
witnessing i don't know how far this
will go and what are the consequences is
going to be like the americans are not
happy clearly
i mean
i mean giving a big f-16 upgrade to
pakistan is is like crossing a certain
line right it's like going back to the
days of the cold war think about it the
americans always accuse indians
india
of having a 20th century mentality of
they accuse india always of having a
cold war mentality well this particular
step that the americans have taken is
nothing but cold war mentality this is
the kind of thing they used to do during
the cold war the 20th century aiding
pakistan supporting pakistan against
india
and they have reopened that playbook so
it is the americans
who are who have a cold war mentality
and they are opening the same playbook
so that's where we are yeah the
relations are not good between india and
the us there will still be cooperation
on a number of matters especially when
it concerns china but in but the
americans want india to bend over
backwards and do whatever they say in
all
aspects of india's foreign policy which
is not going to work
and india is now rising india's gdp grew
by 13 point something percent in the
first quarter of 2022.
that is something which is sets of alarm
bells in the west the west doesn't want
india to rise the west wants india to
stay remain a middle
income i mean a middle
sized economy mid-sized economy not a
big economy 5 trillion would be a
terrible disaster for them 10 trillion
with the end of the world for them they
don't want india to go the china way
china rose and india has all the
potential to rise and that's why they
will do everything they can to keep
hindering india and keep
putting you know roadblocks in india's
way so india will have to find ways to
deal with this so this is what we are
witnessing this is what we are
witnessing so india has most likely
refused to become part of the trade
pillar of the indo-pacific economic
framework
in response to the various american
actions that are clearly hostile to
india
okay kali says why are china disengaging
from line of actual control flash points
does
this is mr putin involved in mediating
the dispute between india and china will
india cancel the upcoming military
exercise that was going to be held in
uttarakhand with u.s military after this
this engagement ayush says
why is army the indian army reorienting
forces to boost combat readiness along
the lac
sector also india and china troops begin
disengagement from the gogra hot springs
region in ladakh what's going on okay
okay
what's going on is this
this coming week
i think on thursday and friday there is
the sco summit
uh shanghai cooperation summit i think
in
one of the central asian countries i
don't remember which one which with
uzbekistan
is somewhere there yeah
so there is the shanghai cooperation
summit that's going to happen
this coming week thursday and friday
and
mr modi prime minister modi is going to
most likely be meeting president ping
now
before such a meet it is it is
appropriate to take some you know
de-escalation measures you know token
gesture of kind of yeah we you know we
will get along together that sort of
thing so what the chinese always do is
this
look at it this way think about it the
chinese have the next five years
calendar in front of them they know
which are the major submits in which the
indian prime minister and the chinese
president have to meet and that's when
they want to indulge in some diplomacy
and maybe um you know get things done
so they have a five-year calendar in
front of them
so based on the calendar they make
various incursions along the line of
control and they hold certain points
that are disputed and you know
india claims it as its own and the
chinese say no it's our ours and they
essentially indulge in provocations and
they wait until a summit is going to
happen and then they pull back in order
to make it look like you know we are
being uh
you know we are being very accommodating
to you
they first create a problem and then
before a summit they pull back so as to
look in front of the whole world like
they are being very accommodating and
very gracious that's what they do
so that's what we are witnessing right
now
because there is a summit coming up in
just a few days that's why the chinese
are now withdrawing and they are saying
it's a mutual withdrawal even india is
withdrawing from the place and we have
beer escalating the whole matter which
is indeed the case so india is also
withdrawing they are also withdrawing
from the place so for some time it's
going to be unoccupied for most
intents and purposes and in the future
they may choose to do it again what they
have done you know
so that is the situation there is a
summit coming up and that's why this
disengagement has happened is russia
involved in mediation not at all russia
has no business being involved in this
and they know it very well the russians
will not
poke their nose where it doesn't belong
yeah mr putin won't do that so russia is
not involved in any mediation of this
the lac dispute between india and china
for other things maybe there is there
could be some involvement which which
may not be made public
but for the lsa issues it's between
india and china purely
will india cancel some upcoming military
exercise in the torah hunt with the u.s
military after this disengagement i
don't see any reason why we should do
that
i don't see any reason why india should
do such a thing
uh
why is army reorienting forces to boost
combat readiness in arunachal pradesh
because we should always be combat ready
because we can never trust the chinese
it's very simple
so we are always in the process of
reorienting forces and maintaining the
highest amount of combat readiness to
deal with any kind of chinese
misadventure right so that's why we do
it
so that's the situation along the line
of actual control the gogra hot springs
region if you want to see where this
gogura hot springs region is let's take
a look at it on the map yes
it's on the line of actual control uh
let's go to the map quickly briefly
here is the map so let's go
to northern india to the
dark region so the gogura hot springs
region is about 125 kilometers east of
the city of lay
the city of la is the capital of the
union territory of ladakh
so the lay is over here yes and gogra is
about 125 kilometers east of lay and it
is to the north of the pangong
lake
right
and that is obviously part of indian
territory but it's on the line of actual
control because china occupies parts of
aksai chin etc illegally and we will
deal with it that in due course of time
so this is the gogura region right it's
as you can see uh let's take a look at
the satellite uh terrain
uh image
this is the google region and this is
where the disengagement is currently
happening
so it's all because of the upcoming
summit and the chinese want to make it
look like they are being very gracious
and very kind and very accommodating
which they are not this is the standard
good old trick that they always play
so it's nothing new for india
vinu says
is afghanistan's taliban regime pro
pakistan like everybody was saying last
year or is it pro india
what is taliban's foreign policy you had
said in august 2021 the taliban is not
anti-india and india should find ways to
cooperate with taliban
has your prediction proved accurate
okay
is the if is afghanistan's taliban
regime pro pakistan like everyone was
saying
do you think it's pro pakistan no
the taliban regime is absolutely not pro
pakistan
they may have been created by the
pakistanis yes in the 1990s through
during the time of being bhutto etc by
the isi
and all but the taliban are almost
exclusively pashtuns and they're all
pashtun nationalists and they have a
massive territorial dispute with
pakistan
they seek the so-called
region back the northwest frontier
province khaibar pakhtunwa all those
regions they seek them back yes
that is the legacy of the british raj
actually
i will not go into the story so there is
a big territorial dispute between
pakistan and afghanistan and the taliban
resent the fact that the pakistanis
think that they still own them and they
can still control afghanistan which is
not happening
and you can you can see you know
intermittent reports from time to time
of border clashes between afghanistan
and
the pakistanis yes
so that's that's an ongoing thing and if
you want to see the kind of sentiment
that the people of afghanistan have
towards pakistan you only need to see
the the reaction in the aftermath of
various cricket matches yeah the afghans
hate pakistan
yeah so the taliban is not pro-pakistan
is it pro-india not quite pro-india but
it is certainly more pro-india than pro
pro pakistan
i mean
india has is still training various
afghan officials maybe soldiers etc
yeah i'm not sure to what extent it's
happening but recently i had seen some
news of
of a plane that landed in in kabul from
delhi with trained officers
which is clearly officers that are under
the taliban regime yeah so there is
cooperation happening india has reopened
various
embassies or whatever in afghanistan to
some extent with the full cooperation
and approval of the taliban and the
taliban they have no issue with india
absolutely not yeah
so it is not exactly a pro-india regime
but it's
much
more
friendly and positively inclined towards
india than it is towards pakistan
yeah now the other part of the question
or what is taliban's foreign policy the
path alibaba doesn't have don't have
much of a foreign policy
the welcome investments in afghanistan
whoever does it whether it is china or
russia or india they have invited india
to continue what india was doing you
know building up afghanistan building
afghanistan infrastructure and all that
and they have i'm sure uh
given assurances of say of uh
security and all that
so that's
that's the limited foreign policy they
have they don't want much interference
in their nation they want to govern
their nation as they see fit and that's
what's happening
uh i had said in august 2021 yes the
the american withdrawal from afghanistan
happened in august 2021 they just pulled
out overnight without informing anyone
right almost like that's what happened
it was a period of great chaos in
afghanistan yeah and all those terrible
scenes on the kabul runway airport and
all that uh so i had said that at the
time i had done two or three live
streams about afghanistan of the
afghanistan crisis and i had indeed said
like vinu says at the time that the
taliban is not anti-india they don't
hold any grudges against india they may
actually be positively inclined towards
india because
the pashtuns the afghans have
have benefited a lot from what from the
development work india has done in
afghanistan the americans
they poured in a lot of money into
afghanistan but that was mostly used to
give bribes and to buy politicians
the investments that india has done in
afghanistan actually serve the afghan
people
whether it is dams whether it is
public buildings whether it is
investments in agriculture it all serves
the common man woman and child
and in the taliban their families have
also benefited from that so if you if
you look at the individual taliban foot
soldier and even the the officers etc
they would actually have some some kind
of positive feeling towards india
so i had said at the time that the
taliban is not in india and you can see
in the past year
has taliban done a single thing that is
anti-india
you can see lots of clashes with
pakistan but do you have you seen a
single thing that is in india there were
many indian officials in kabul when this
entire thing was happening when the
scenario was unfolding the taliban did
not stop india from taking out all of
its citizens they did not you know
uh
hinder india in any way and they
cooperated with india even at that time
in the time of chaos and after their
that time there has not been a single
anti-india action taken by the taliban
so i had indeed said that india needs to
find india should find ways to cooperate
with the taliban i think this is
happening at various levels
it will not be publicized
it will not be you know
tom tommed from the rooftops but yes
it's it's indeed happening
at a variety at various levels
so i think my prediction has indeed
proved accurate i was say i mean the
things i said
it actually uh most people did not agree
with it
most people thought that taliban will be
a major security issue for india and
they will see a upsurge of terrorism and
violence and kashmir in various parts of
india absolutely none of that has
happened like i said it would not happen
so i think my predictions vis-a-vis
afghanistan have come have proven to be
more or less accurate
yeah yeah so that's what i can say about
this matter
anonymous says is germany also occupied
by the usa just like japan and who wrote
the german constitution
my goodness the questions you are asking
is germany also occupied by the u.s just
like japan yes the americans have a
number of permanent new military bases
on german soil
and these bases have been in place on
german territory on german soil since
1945. this is called permanent
occupation permanent military occupation
look it up
some people will say where are the
references look it up yourself my dear
friends i'm not going to spoon feed you
fact check what i'm saying i am making a
claim i am saying that there have there
are permanent u.s military bases in
germany that have been in place since
the end of the second world war go ahead
and do a fact check do a little bit of
research of your own
so yes germany is also
occupied military occupation by the us
just like japan yes that's part one of
the question that's your answer look it
up
the second part of the question is who
wrote the german consideration
what do you think wrote the german
constitution okay let's go into that
story
uh so
the german constitution um there was
something called the frankfurt documents
or whatever it was called this was a set
of guidelines and principles and
documents
that were drafted by the western
occupying powers
the us
the uk
france and whoever else it was yeah who
were occupying west germany
so after the world war two germany was
partitioned divided into the eastern
block and the western bloc the eastern
bloc the east german east germany was
essentially occupied by the ussr
and west germany was occupied by the
americans and their their minions the uk
france etc yeah that's what happened so
germany was partitioned
now
when it comes to west germany a new
constitution was created
based on these frankfurt documents i
think they were called
1948 49 somewhere around that time that
the americans essentially
gave to the germans then a constituent
assembly was
selected not elected selected
a constituent assembly was selected
and this constituent assembly took those
documents the frankfurt documents
and then they formulated the so-called
constitution based on that
and before the constitution was became
became came to came into force it was
given the seal of approval the official
seal of approval formally approved by
the occupying western powers so this
entire process was a sham there was
nothing democratic about it
and the constitution was you can say
that some germans drafted it but it was
all done under the strict and direct
supervision of the occupying americans
and essentially it is nothing but
something that the americans have
created yeah so they made it look like
it was a kind of democratic process
there was a constituent assembly we have
done it through the due process
yeah
due process yeah that was a sham due
process
so in the case of japan the constitution
was directly written by the americans
in the case of germany there was an
intermediate you know it was written by
proxy but again by the americans the
german constitution is nothing but a
constitution that was drafted and
approved
by the americans and that's what is
still enforced in germany today so
germany just like japan is a nation that
is under permanent american occupation
it is not a free nation and you have
elections and they elect chancellors and
all but it's all under
a constitution
that has been created by a foreign
occupying power so do you call this
democracy really really
i i know the system is continued for 70
plus years but it's not a democratic
system
says i was researching about global
superpowers the us the united states
surprised me the number of military
bases alliances treaty treaties etc they
have is way too huge well
good job sir you your eyes have been
opened
the number of military bases they have
across the world is incredible
they essentially occupy half the world
more than half the world the americans
military bases so uh continuing it's
nearly impossible to beat the us
how can india replace u.s hegemony and
become become a dominant global
superpower by all means
uh includes economy military bases
allies soft power etc
right good question
uh yes the us like you're saying it's
nearly impossible to beat the us yeah
we have to understand that there are
cycles in
history typically an empire a superpower
is an empire the superpower is like a
global empire
typically empires have a limited life
span
some have a lifespan of 100 years some
200 years some 300 years and you see
these imperial cycles rise and fall rise
and fall rise and fall throughout
history this is a pattern that you see
over and over and over and over again in
history whether it is in china whether
it is in india whether it's in europe or
anywhere else empires rise and they
eventually inevitably decline and fall
because of internal reasons not because
somebody from outside comes and destroys
them or defeats them which happens
sometimes but typically it is because of
internal reasons
yeah they they
essentially eat away at themselves and
destroy themselves they lose what
made them great that always happens
whether it's the roman empire whether it
is the mongol empire
whether it is various chinese empires
various indian empires eventually it
always declines this is what we are
seeing now in real time when it comes to
the anglo-saxon empire which is a
continuation of the british empire the
british
empire that on which the sun never set
yeah the the u.s empire is a
continuation of that that's what we call
a superpower it is now
visibly in decline
so the question is how can india you
replace u.s hegemony and become a
dominant superpower
india has to bide its time
india has to build its economy india has
to work very very hard every single
citizen needs to contribute on his in
his or her own way
to the nation's economy as the economy
grows india's hard power will grow
right and when it comes to
replacing an empire
we can see various historical examples
think about the nanda empire
in the third century bc it was the third
century thereabouts yeah third century
bc the nanda empire which was uh
headquartered in partly putra
the nanda empire was a massive empire
that spanned much of india
it was so massive and so powerful
that alexander sold soldiers mutinied
alexander had rampaged across europe and
western asia he had annihilated the
incredibly powerful persian empire and
yet when he came to the borderlands of
india his soldiers mutinied because they
knew it was suicide to ge to go further
eastwards and face
the might of the nanda empire
so it was so massive alexander could not
stand a chance against it that's how
powerful the nanda empire was and yet
within 20 years
it was gone
and what replaced the nanda empire
the mauryan empire which went on to
become even more powerful
in just in less than two decades an
entire empire
so powerful that it was
too powerful for alexander that entire
empire vanished evaporated and was
replaced
by
the empire of chandragupta maurya
this one
young man chandragupta maurya
with the help of his great mentor vishnu
gupta
in less than two decades replaced
this pre-existing great empire
it can happen
it can be done
of course you need somebody as as
vigorous and as capable as chandragupta
maurya
and you need
a great brain behind
such a man you need a vishnu
of your own if you had have that
combination anything can happen and you
can see such things happen over and over
again
look at how massive the chinese empire
was and the mongols were this ragtag
bunch of tribes who were always
being
made to fight each other by the chinese
and then one fine day
this young man comes out of the mongol
you know uh
wild wild territory
his name was temujin he went on to unify
the mongol tribes under one banner they
called him chingis ching is khan and he
went on to annihilate china
within one lifetime
anything is possible
so i'm not saying that india needs to go
ching is khan on the american empire
i'm not saying india needs to go
chandragupta maury
u.s empire the u.s empire is in decline
it's already in decline we can see it
declining they are trying to fight it
right now but it's in decline so india
is on the other hand rising the economy
is growing there is so much energy and
potential in india
so much scope for
progress
so india needs to
take it easy
not
let me take that back not take it easy
india needs to keep its head down abide
its time and work as hard as it possibly
can and when i say india i mean you all
stop wasting time raise your standards
work hard work hard work hard
and see what happens in 20 years time
the world will be unrecognizable that's
what's going to happen
okay enough geopolitics for a while for
a while let's take something else
saurabh says is there any evidence of
rice agriculture in india
17 lakh years ago someone said this to
me and it sounds weird
uh saurabh you know if somebody says
there was there is evidence of rice
agriculture 17 lakh years ago that
i i am glad it sounds weird to you
because it doesn't make any sense
homo sapiens
our species is three lakh years old yeah
17 lakh years means 1.7 million almost 2
million years before today there can't
be any agriculture because there was no
evolved species of humans at the time
agriculture rice agriculture is one
is 17 000 years old the oldest evidence
of of agriculture in india proper
cultivation dates back to about 15 000
something we see in the indian
subcontinent where was this discovered
in sri lanka
in the heartlands in the in the
highlands of sri lanka
so let me give you the let me let me
show it to you for for a change let me
show you some reference
uh let me put something on the screen
let me show you the article and you can
look it up and find the
references within
so this is an article by dr anil sori
how old is indian agriculture right
google it and you'll find it so what do
we find here
um
when did it actually begin etc etc all
right this this one here beyond the
holocene agriculture in the please store
sim
so
uh
to trace the trajectory from incipient
cultivation as a dry crop etc we must
journey south indeed as far down as the
southern part of sri lanka to the
mesmerizingly beautiful horton plains
national park to be precise here there
is evidence of cattle herding and
grazing etc etc cultivation of edible
plants and early management of barley
and oats from
15500 bce
that is 17 and a half thousand years
before today and you can read the rest
of the article i will not go and do it
but i i invite you all to do that
so the earliest evidence of cultivation
of crops in india systematic cultivation
of crops dates back to 17 and a half
thousand years before today in sri lanka
now some of you will say sri lanka is a
different country talk about india
my dear friends seventeen thousand years
ago
the ice age
was in force
the sea levels were much lower than it
what they are today india and sri lanka
were a single land mass
so sri lanka was
physically part of the indian
subcontinent at that time
do you understand that
sri lanka was part of india it was
connected there was no break there was
no ocean between india and srilanka it
was just the same land mass
it was part of the south indian
peninsula sri lanka all right
so the oldest evidence of agriculture
rice agriculture in india and most
likely in the entire world is from sri
lanka present-day sri lanka 17 and a
half thousand years before today not 17
lakh somebody must have read this and
they must have quoted it wrong all right
so that is the answer
rishabh says why did zoroastrians from
iran escape to india through the sea
route why didn't they come through the
land route even if some did come through
the land
route which i believe why is there no
evidence regarding this there is no
evidence because they came through the
sea route
the zoroastrians the persians our
persian
parsi brethren and sister in who escaped
from iran during the arabic invasion and
during the arabic invasion of iran they
escaped to india
by ships and by boats
and they landed in in gujarat in western
india in a place which is now called
zanja sanjan which was named after their
hometown of zanjan in persia
shall we take a look at wherever it is
because why not we we love the map don't
we
where's the map here's the map here it
is
where's the map
here's the map okay let's take a look at
where is zanjan in iran
in zanjan
here is the the town of zanjan in in
persia it's in northern persia right
it's near the caspian sea region
and these persians these parsees
zoroastrians who escaped to india in
order to preserve their religion and
their culture
they landed somewhere in western
india
in in sanjan which is i don't know
somewhere here i believe
and there
some of them live in in navsari
walsard have you heard of pharaoh sarah
faro balsa freddie mercury
a famous singer so he was indian
zoroastrian and so on okay so the
question is why did the parsees the
austrians escape through the sea route
why not through the land road because
the arabs did not have the capability to
pursue them by sea the arabs did not
invade persia
through the sea route the arabs did not
have any naval capabilities the arabs
invaded
persia through present-day iran and
there were multiple battles it was not
an overnight thing but it was very rapid
the arab advance into iran was very
rapid
so the iranians the persians who wanted
to uh
escape they did so through the sea route
because the arabs had no ability
to pursue them by sea if they had tried
to escape to india why are
balochistan etc presented pakistan
temporarily what is pakistan then the
arabs could have pursued them and hunted
them down but because they escaped by
sea the arabs were not able to catch up
with them because the arabs did not have
any naval capabilities and that's what
happened that's how they end the the
persians ended up in
western india in gujarat and we know the
story we know the story after that i
hope you all know the story
so that's the answer that's why they
escaped through the sea route not the
land road
sahil says
where did all the huns parthians koshans
skythians etc who invaded india where
did they disappear
are they still living in india
how can we identify them
i want to meet them um i want to meet
them the kitthyans the koshans the
parthians and so on so forth
see it's like this my dear friends even
the greeks the yawners invaded india
they made kingdoms in north west india
present day i mean gandalf present day
afghanistan and parts of present-day
pakistan punjab and so on so forth even
western india gujarat
swarastha et cetera for some time was
was ruled by the yawanas the ionians
which is the greeks and so on
then these indo-greek kingdoms
went out of power
and they were replaced by these
keithians the mahakshatrapa the sketians
later the kushans up north kanishka and
his his merry men and so on so forth
right and then there were these various
invasions into india
which were first of all repelled by the
great gupta emperors including skanda
gupta during the time of his father
kumar of the whole story there but
eventually after the gupta era ended the
hunts were also able to make inroads
into india there was a very cruel king
called mehirakula very evil guy very bad
guy and there were some good honey kings
as well eventually and
eventually even the hunik age ended so
the question is a very good question
where are all these guys
the yavanas where did they go
did they all go back to greece
absolutely not
what about the parthians the people the
parthians were anyway uh vedic clan the
prithu clan so they were not foreigners
right the horns
were foreigners they came from central
asia they looked different they had
elongated heads and they had typical uh
what we call features yes the
greeks the yawanas where
well they came from greece the ionian
sea region yeah uh the questions and
these key things were of indian origin
so they are not really
some some geniuses always tell me
abhijit you are so wrong the kushans
were the yuchi the chinese called the
muchi and they were turks or whatever
they were whatever they were there for
central asia how can you say they're
indians you're so wrong
the koshans
lived in
what was once called uttarakuru
right
who founded uttarakuru
who lived in uttarakuru
various vedic clans
the skittions they lived in what we once
called uttara madra
they were also of indian
origin if you look at history from this
narrow perspective you will see a
certain version of history but if you
took take a look at a bigger time frame
your entire perspective will change and
you will see so much more information
so please try to look at the picture
holistically instead of looking at
narrow time periods and then giving gyan
okay so what happened
the huns
the the kushans the kytheons the greeks
they all assimilated into the indian
population
they didn't go back anywhere
they had the the greeks stayed they
ruled over parts of india for two three
hundred years
the kushans ruled for almost half a
second half a
ruled very well in western india in
gujarat they were the the lords and
protectors and servants of the great
ancient jyotirling shrine of sumnat
so the
of ruling mahaksha india gujarat
swarastha et cetera they were very good
rulers by all accounts
and even the hoon slater were very good
rulers
the great um
the hunnic ruler vyagaramukh
who ruled in bin mal
in
rajasthan in the rajasthan region
he was the patron
of the great
scientist brahma gupta
a hunnic king was the patron of the
great indian scientist astronomer
mathematician brahma gupta so all these
kings
all these rulers eventually became
indian they they would have married
indian ladies in among royalty
right this guy uh
viagra mukha
he belonged to the sri chapa dynasty
which was an indian dynasty not a hunik
dynasty so it looks like he took took
the name of it of an indian dynasty
right and so on so they gradually
assimilated and after the
see they would not have come in enormous
numbers in india
right typically these invasions there is
an invasive invasive force maybe 10 20
30 000 people and they would be good
warriors and that's why they won because
india was temporarily in a in a place
in a time period where there was
disunity that happens from time to time
and that's how these invaders were able
to succeed but eventually they ruled
over india they became good rulers they
assimilated into the indian population
so where are they today they are part of
the indian population
most people in northern india western
india whether it is afghanistan whether
it is the temporary nation of pakistan
whether it is gujarat rajasthan punjab
aryana and other parts of india all the
way to the south etc
everybody would have maybe one percent
of of of
yavana blood maybe one percent
koshan blood maybe one percent blood
maybe three percent kitten blood
and so on
they are nowhere to be found they are
all among us they are us now they have
become part of us
if you are in any of these parts of
india you would have
a little bit
small fractional amount of ancestry from
these ancient peoples
and that's that's the answer right you
can't identify them anymore they are you
you most likely would have a little bit
of ancestry
and as would most of us
yeah
arya says is it true
that most of the egyptian mummies are
gone
because the british ate them
the truth is
that many
egyptian mummies are gone because the
british and other europeans eat them
and i think most people will be shocked
to hear this
most people will be shocked to hear and
most people will not believe what i'm
saying
yeah
the practice of eating
egyptian mummies
began i believe in the 12th century
so around this time
mummies were exported
from egypt see at that time egypt was
ruled by the arabs
the entire culture and religion of egypt
had changed and there was no sacredness
associated anymore with the egyptian
mummies the mummies of their ancestors
right so
egypt used to sell
mummies to the european nations at that
time the the
various
uh exchanges cultural exchanges
and other exchanges between the islamic
world the arabic world and the in the
christian or european world were already
going on right and that's how the indian
knowledge was transferred to to europe
indian mathematics and science and all
that so at that time the arabs were
ruling the mamluks were ruling egypt yes
and the europeans were very curious
about egyptian mummies and these mamluks
and the
whoever was ruling would sell mummies to
europeans
and europeans they had this weird thing
that
at that time there was no medicine right
there was only things people believed
various things so it was believed that
these mummies were the mummies of
egyptian kings
and it was believed that mummies
they held spirit
the spirit you know the life spirit of
the ancient egyptian kings and therefore
if you consume that then your health
will improve and will become much better
so the european royalty used to consume
powders made by grinding up egyptian
mummies
and that practice eventually made its
way into the civilian
non-royal non-aristocratic population as
well and after after a century or two
the egyptians
they imposed a ban on exporting mummies
but by the time fake mummies were
created and that practice continued
and even the 18th and 19th century you
would have
centuries you would have these various
egyptians selling mummies on the
roadside you know
that sort of thing
so yes a significant number of egyptian
mummies were ground up into powder and
consumed i think there was a powder
called mumiya or something that the
europeans used to eat
and they believed it would give them
better health it would cure various
illnesses and diseases and all that and
there was a lot of cannibalism in europe
you know
the
british royalty
they would be given various ointments
and medicines
made from human skulls
and various
ointments made from human fat would be
used as ointments or to treat diseases
like gout and various other things you
know
so that's the kind of practice you had
in europe for for a very long time
uh human skull extracts were given to
british royalty until the beginning of
the 20th century
yeah so from the 12th century until the
20th century these barbaric
primitive brutal
strange bizarre practices continued in
europe and in the uk
cannibalism actual cannibalism
so i'm not sure how many mummies are
consumed and afterwards what happened is
that mummies became a big craze in in
europe and there used to be these mummy
unwrapping parties
so a bunch of rich people would get
together they would get drunk and then
they would they would have procured a
mummy
and then they would unwrap the mummy and
make it naked and that was something
supposedly entertainment for them
and that that showed you how rich you
were because it was quite expensive to
procure a mummy you know mummies by the
time were quite rare and they were not
radially available so if you could
procure a mummy which came from egypt it
may it showed your status as a very
wealthy person and then you would invite
all your wealthy friends rich friends
and you would all have a party or get
drunk and then you would unwrap the
mummy and
that sort of thing so i don't know what
kind of incredibly bizarre practices
were
were in vogue
in europe
but yes it is indeed true that europeans
consumed
egyptian mummies
and
even fake egyptian mummies
so
cannibalism cannibalism was an accepted
practice in europe until the 20th
century i don't know how it is now i'm
sure it's not
it's not there now but yeah
interesting isn't it my dear friends
okay that's a whole lot of questions
vampires i'm scared now akash says woman
vampire skeleton found in poland does it
make the stories we heard about vampire
is true
um shubham says what's your take on the
vampire skeleton found in poland jai
says
what's your thought on recent
archaeological discovery of female
vampire skeleton in poland do vampires
exist
and vinay says sir female vampire
threatened discovered in poland
what is a vampire and how can a human
become a vampire i am so scared now oh
my god
okay
let's deal with this question
uh let us put the news item on the
screen shall we yeah let's do that let
me share my screen
female vampires current so what did you
find let's take a look at what was
actually discovered
right uh
come on screen here we are let's remove
this and let's see the screen
so it says a 17th century vampire grave
discovered in poland
of a skeleton with a sickle across her
neck so this unfortunate person is a
lady young lady apparently
and she was buried with this hooked
sickle across her neck
uh and are there more images there it is
can you see this
so this unfortunate person was buried in
this manner clearly somebody put a
sickle across the neck and uh
the vampire folklore was very much
prevalent in in europe especially
eastern europe poland is in eastern
europe north of uh
of romania transylvania where these
legends actually perhaps originate the
nosferatu
legend if you watch the movie dracula
and so on
yeah so this is what they discovered so
what does this signify does it mean that
this unfortunate lady was an actual
vampire
did she drink human blood does it mean
that
so here's what it means
see uh
in the old days people did not
understand the uh
various diseases that happened in some
cases
certain diseases
looked like someone is under vampire
attack there was an illness called
consumption
consumption in which people would lose
blood through cough they would cough up
blood
and slowly and slowly they would become
paler and they would look like they have
lost a lot of blood because their lungs
would be cuffing of blood consumption is
today called tuberculosis
all right
so
there was already this ancient myth of
the nosferatu in the transverse
transylvania region of romania
and europeans were extremely
superstitious yes
they believed in this these demonic
entities called vampires and then you
had various
in inexplainable diseases that would
come in from time to time and they would
blame it on these supernatural
forces
and then you would have people who would
have tuberculosis consumption their
clothes would be bloody you know they
would wake up in the morning from night
and they would be pale and they would
have blood on their mouth and
neck and all that it would look like
they have been
assaulted by a vampire in the night
and the belief was that if one if a
person has been bitten by a vampire
then after they die they don't really
die they become the undead and they come
back in the night out of the grave and
they attack other living people that was
the belief
right and so to prevent that from
happening they would
there would be like a couple of things
they would do they would put a stake
through the heart of the dead person
in the hope that the person won't rise
again and
in in some cases they would put a big
stone or a brick in the mouth of a dead
person
so that they can't come back and bite
somebody yeah
and in some cases you would have this
sort of thing they would put a sickle
across the neck of the deceased person
in the hope that that would prevent the
person from uh arising
from their
from the sleep yeah from from the from
the grave
various uh
various myths and superstations so what
is the origin of the vampire myth
so the vampire is a person who has died
but who is not who is not completely
dead
that person still is able to arise at
night and they come and pray on the
living and drink their blood this is in
a way
similar to the uh concept
of the supernatural bri being called the
pret
in indian ancient indian mythology so
the pratha is a spirit
that has a very strong longing for
certain things you know a spirit that
has been
not been fulfilled in its life and had a
bad death or whatever and it has a
certain longing maybe it
it has a curse on it so it it longs for
blood or some other things like that you
know unhealthy longings and the same
mythology is found in southeast asia in
china they call it the hungry ghost
and it's so the vampire myth seems to be
similar to these these myths so certain
myths they persist across time and space
and all that so that's the thing so that
is what this vampire skeleton discovery
means what it means is that she this
unfortunate lady this person was not
really a vampire obviously but people
must have believed that she's a vampire
because of something like that maybe
she'd suffered from tuberculosis maybe
she had consumption when maybe they
thought that she may rise again from the
dead and that's why they put a sickle
across her neck when they buried her
so let the archaeologists do more
research they can maybe sample the chest
area you know the ribcage area and see
if they can find any uh any any evidence
of tuberculosis bacilli
over there in the microscopic uh
whatever they can dust up from there and
maybe we'll have a better idea of what
was going on maybe she had tuberculosis
consumption and maybe maybe that's why
it looked like
maybe the people felt that she is a
candidate from the for becoming a
nosferatu a vampire in her afterlife
yeah
pages says why do more and more people
believe that china is the origin of
buddhism it's very simple
marketing propaganda
you take a lie you construct a lie and
then you repeat it over and over and
over again and you don't do it yourself
alone you recruit a thousand other
people to do the same thing so now you
have a thousand people repeating the
same lie over and over and over again
and that's when lies become the truth
that is how propaganda works that's how
marketing works
just bombard the same message over and
over again the chinese are trying to
claim buddhism for their own now the
chinese communist party says that the
buddhism is a chinese religion
they say it's a chinese indigenous
religion
right and if you look at various uh
uh western depictions of
of the lord gotham buddha they depict
gotham buddha as a person with eastern
asian features with chinese-like
features not indian features yeah
that's the popular emanation in the west
of what buddha was of gotham buddha
and the chinese are doing their best to
to
take this further
so they what they want to do is they
want to capture the buddhism tourism
market
there is a huge
uh
potential
for religious tourism vis-a-vis buddhism
and the chinese want to capture that
the the heartland of buddhism is magadha
it is the magadha region the partly both
region the gaya region the lumbini
region right
that region
and the place where the lord buddha
attained enlightenment
uh
the bodhi tree where it was that is all
in in bihar right in in present-day
bihar that should be where all the
buddhism tourism happens
but unfortunately
uh it's not very well maintained and all
that it's hard for tourists to reach
there and the accommodation etc is not
great and so on the chinese will do
their best to to capture the market
they will
build brilliant beautiful stupas and
pagodas
and and five-star hotels
and give all the facilities to people to
come there and that's how they will
benefit from the
international buddhist tourism market
so the chinese want to capture it even
when it comes to the shaolin temple
two or three years ago if you went to
the shaolin temple website it was
clearly said on the shaolin temple's
official website
that the
first patriarch
of the shaolin temple is the indian monk
buddhi dharma and he is the founder of
kung fu
he is the person who taught what is now
kung fu to the chinese it was clearly
mentioned there today if you go to the
website of the shaolin temple
it is very hard to find any such
reference
yeah
so everything all the truth is being
expunged
and
a new
narrative is being woven
and and people
[Music]
it's very it's very easy to sway
people's minds with with good marketing
so that's what the chinese are doing and
i'm i wonder why india is not doing
anything because the truth lies with
india
gotham buddha was indian
right
and buddhism was born was was
it emerged out of india both the dharma
which is one of the
one of the flavors of overall dharma
under the dharmic umbrella both the
dharma emerged in india
so india is the homeland of buddhism of
both the dharma of lord buddha and all
that
it's it's a golden opportunity it's like
low hanging fruit waiting to be plucked
but nothing is being done so the chinese
are taking advantage of that and now
more and more people believe that china
is the origin of buddhism
especially in the west
so it's something we can still rectify
you know if the government gets its act
together especially the ministry of
culture and tourism which i would say is
one of the
one of the uh
not very well performing ministries of
the government of india
krishna says how come the japanese
embraced buddhism but were hostile
towards christianity
how come
what is the reason
while it's like this my dear friends
when it comes to
dharma
both dharma dharma
the japanese found that people
who became practitioners of of dharma
whether it is both the dharma or
whatever form
they remained 100 japanese
and they were completely devoted to the
service of their motherland
japan
yes
you may not know this but for centuries
in japan the consumption of meat was
prohibited because of the influence of
dharma
and it is a misconception that the japan
that the japanese are pure buddhists you
will find every single
non-buddhist
hindu deity divinity
represented in japan
whether it is saraswati who is called
bin zythen whether it is lord ganesh who
has japanese name whether it is lord
shiva whether it is lord mahakal whether
it is lakshmi every single non-buddhist
hindu god and goddess is represented in
the japanese polytheistic pantheon it is
now called buddhism yeah anyhow that's a
whole different story so
i think uh
buddhism or dharma
entered japan at least 1500 years before
today it entered japan via china so the
chinese were deeply interested in
becoming dharmic yes their kings their
emperors would send requests to indian
kings and emperors for india to send
buddhist scholars bathing scholars to
china who would then go there and
translate sutras and sanskrit texts into
chinese and slowly the chinese became
indianized right you still see that
today whether the chinese like it or not
it's there
a significant amount of the chinese
culture comes out of india they have
absorbed it and made it their own
then that propagated further east into
japan why china of course a few indian
scholars
dharma gurus also did go into japan and
set up monasteries there with royal
approval yes it happened
so uh
buddhism so to say has been in japan for
at least 1 500 years and the japanese
always observed that when japanese
citizens civilians kings
or samurai warriors etc
they became practitioners of dharma
whether buddhism whatever they remained
completely devoted to the service of
their motherland
now when christianity entered japan
about 500 or so years ago roughly
roughly devotee
the japanese observed that those
japanese who became christians
don't take my word for it look it up
yourself
the japanese observed that those
japanese who became christians
tended to become anti-nationals
and they would
indulge in activities that would be
counter
productive to the japanese national
interest
and that's why the japanese became very
hostile towards christianity
this is a fact look it up yourself fact
check me i will not give you sources you
can look it up for yourself it's all
available online it's all available in
the public domain do a little bit of
fact checking please go ahead all right
feel free
summarth says how should india deal with
central asian countries like kazakhstan
kyrgyzstan turkey et cetera turkey has
been involved in anti-india activities
and terrorism as well should india be
more assertive or turkey is not a
central asian country
turkey is not a central asian country
let's put the map on yes
let's do that let's take a look at what
central asia actually is
uh for some reason i'm looking at
gujarat let's close that
here's the map
look where is turkey
it's a mediterranean nation it's over
here
what is central asia all of this is
central asia kazakhstan
turkmenistan etc all of this is central
asia turkey is way way to the west it's
a mediterranean nation it occupies
present it occupies anatolia
right
uh
so
so let's forget about turkey for now we
know what turkey is up to turkey has
always been an anti-india nation more or
less
in the past
70 or so years
the question is how should india deal
with the central asian nations like
kazakhstan
uzbekistan
the other central asian nations are
turkic nations
tajikistan is an indo-iranian nation the
people they speak you could say they are
an extension of greater iran tajikistan
okay
uh the other nations whether it is
turkmenistan uzbekistan kazakhstan
um east turkestan currently occupied by
china etc these are all turkic nations
now india
see if you if you look here let's take
the example of kyrgyzstan
can you see where kyrgyzstan is
it's right north of india it's almost
like a stone's throw away from india but
nobody in india knows that this nation
exists
it's practically a neighboring country
of india
just a few kilometers north
okay let's see the distance from lay
from lei
okay for some reason it's about 500 or
so kilometers maybe 700 kilometers which
is not a big distance in in the big
perspective
so kyrgyzstan is here and i would say
that all these nations are very
favorably inclined towards india there
is no
element of of uh hostility towards india
there is no cause for these neighbors
for these nations to have any ill
feeling or ill will towards india yeah
we don't have any border disputes we
don't have shared boundaries
a long long time ago during the time of
genghis khan india
and central asia had a common border
which was around this region in
tajikistan when afghanistan was a part
of india
but that's long gone so all these
nations i i don't see why india can't
have excellent friendly and warm
relations with these nations i think
india should take the time to invest in
uh forming good relations with these
countries maybe we should uh
have direct flights to these nations i
am sure a nation a wonderful nation like
kyrgyzstan could benefit from an influx
of indian tourists yes they have this
wonderful lake over here called the isik
cool lake
very pretty lake and they have a very
beautiful country similarly uh when it
comes to tajikistan very nice
mountainous country uzbekistan is nice
kazakhstan is a huge huge country one of
the most
one of the largest countries in the
world yes so uh there's a great amount
of potential for tourism there's a great
amount of potential for indian
investments in these countries for for
whatever business
opportunities are available there so i
think india should take the time to
engage with these nations nowadays india
is doing that there is this
multi-pronged diplomacy that we are
doing
and some of these nations are part of
the seo the shanghai cooperation uh
organization so that also we can do but
the chinese are involved there so
all of these nations would i would
guarantee you would be much more
favorably inclined towards india than
towards china
yeah and these nations uh russia
considers these nations the central
asian nations to be part of its uh
exclusive sphere of geopolitical
influence and we can leverage that also
because we have excellent relations with
russia so i think india should deal
in a very positive way with these
central asian nations if we can have
direct flights available from various
parts of india i'm sure indian tourists
would love to go there the people there
are very nice very welcoming very warm
yeah
so uh there is a huge
scope huge potential
for uh people-to-people contacts maybe
business contacts and overall warm
diplomatic friendly relations between
these nations and india
so india should
explore these opportunities for sure
siddesh says will european nations
remain united in the coming years
no
if europe is peaceful
and united and has been so in the past
70 years since 1945 it is simply because
the
most powerful
the greatest power in europe today in
western europe today is the united
states
it is the united states through its
puppet organizations nato
and the european union that has
maintained stability and peace
in europe
for its own benefit
right
and the americans actually occupy much
of europe they have nuclear weapons
in various parts of europe american
nuclear power weapons on european
territory on the territory of various
european nations and the americans have
multiple permanent military bases in
various parts of europe so ameri america
essentially occupies in one way or the
other much of western europe and much of
western europe is
controlled in a variety of ways by the
americans
the american power is now declining we
are seeing that
as this happens
europe will become more assertive and
all the old enmities all the old tribal
enmities in europe will re-emerge
there are old disputes
old schools that need to be settled
dating back to the napoleonic wars the
crusades
the balkan wars and so much more it's
it's a tinderbox
as u.s power declines
and as u.s control over europe declines
you're going to see more and more
problems re-emerge in europe so i don't
do not see
europe remaining united
in the coming years
the european union will persist for
maybe a couple of decades maybe three
decades i don't know how long it will
persist but eventually it will all fall
apart europe is
currently united which is
it is done through an external force it
is artificially united these various
peoples they have nothing much in common
and they have a lot
a lot of bad memories of each other
that's gonna re-emerge at some point in
time so i don't see europe remaining
united in the long term
monika says what's your take on yogi at
up chief minister yo
statement that uttar pradesh will become
a one trillion dollar economy state i
think it will happen and i think it
should happen as soon as possible i
think it will be great for india and for
the great state of uttar pradesh if this
happens
it is time that india becomes prosperous
again if you look at uttar pradesh it
once was the heartland the historical
heartland of india
yet the great mahajanapada some of the
most prosperous and most powerful
mahajanapadas where in the heart of up
the coastal mahajanapada
kashi and many more the great kingdom of
ayodhya
is in the heart of up these were some of
the most powerful
kingdoms and empires in india
and some of the most prosperous
regions in india so it is time for the
great people of up and the great state
of up to re-emerge
there is an incredible amount of
potential in uttar pradesh and in
neighboring bihar
bihar is magadha
bihar used to be for thousands of years
the real seat of power in india partly
putra before parliamentary you had raj
graham
these states
where the old
ancient powerhouses politically and
economically of india it is time for
them to re-emerge and there needs to be
this healthy competition between indian
states all of them should aspire to be
one trillion dollar economies and more
than that bihar should do that up should
do that i would like arunachala to do
that in tripura also to do that and
kalinga
orissa to also become a one trillion
dollar economy state right all the
indian states need to have this
wonderful healthy rivalry and
competition amongst each other as to who
will perform the best economically
it's like a sports team in which you're
all working together but you're all
still trying to be the best player in
the team that sort of thing that is
great for the team it's great for the
overall cause
of the team for the campaign that you
are all
working towards yeah so that needs to
happen and uh
i completely
agree with the yogi statement that it's
going to happen it will certainly happen
and i look forward to that happening as
soon as is humanly possible
descendant of rigvedic clan says what is
the transitive brahmi script
dr niraj ray tweeted early wheat
evidence okay let's take one question at
a time yeah what is the transitive
brahma script
uh
transitive brahma script is an
older version
of the brahmi script so if you look at
the uh mainstream consensus literature
about brahmi they say that brahmi
emerged around 500 bc
the brahmani script they
most historians and most textbooks and
history books will say brahmi emerged
around 500 bc
and they say they make this claim that
brahmi is a descendant of the aramaic
script which is a semitic script and
aramaic this this script is a descendant
of the old phoenician script whatever
that is not important right
the problem for for these claims is that
there is an older version of the brahmi
script which they call which is which
could be called the transitive or
transitional
brahmi script which is midway between
the saraswati hindu script and the
brahma script
dr subash khan who has been on on this
channel twice already
in 1990 he published a paper i don't i'm
not sure if i have it here yep he
published a paper in 1990 in uh
in which
he
did a comparison a comparative analysis
the top 10
most frequently
occurring symbols
in the saraswati hindu script or the
indus spelling script and the 10 most
common
symbols in the brahmi script
put them side by side and compare them
and you can see clear similarities
right so it is clear actually that the
brahmi script
emerged from the old script the
saraswati sindhu script and there was a
transitory phase in between
so that is called the transitive branch
script it dates back to about 1500 bc
which predates
the aramaic script because the rmax
crypt emerged around 800 or 900 bc
maybe 850 bc
but the transitive brahmi script
emerged
about 1500 bc much before the birth of
the
aramaic script that totally destroys
this claim that the brahmi script is a
descendant of the aramaic script and it
all came from abroad so that is what the
transitive brahmana script is and much
more research needs to be done but i
think
some people are doing very good progress
on deciphering these sellers for this in
the script there's this gentleman called
yajna devam
i still haven't studied his paper but i
will do it soon yeah so that's good
progress happening
why why is there gandhari statue in
every court in india
so gandhari was this this lady in
ancient india she she
she was the mother of the koravas of the
mahabharata era yeah
she she was married to this uh the the
blind king
and because she in solidarity with her
husband she decided to put a
bandage on her eyes and never open her
eyes again that sort of thing so she had
she was blindfolded and in every indian
court these days you have this
statue this this statue of a lady who is
blindfolded
who's
holding this balance right
so that statue is what they call lady
justice because justice should be blind
should be impartial that sort of thing
so it's not gandhari but yeah
nice joke
dia says curious to know do you have an
editorial assistant or do you do all the
work by yourself do you read all the
comments here which takes a lot of time
or do you read only a few questions and
select good ones
do i have editor or assistant
i have a secret army of minions
who do all the work for me i just sit
here and do nothing
do i read all the comments
i try to read as many comments as i can
it does take a lot of time but i mean if
i want to respect my viewers i should
read all the comments especially the
ones which have the ask a budget
so i actually do that yeah i spend
significant amounts of time reading the
comments and then i select the questions
that make sense you know
there are always lots of great questions
and i can only take like 20 30 questions
per session
so unfortunately you know time is
limited and i'm like i can only take a
few questions so i try to do as many as
i can so i do read all the comments with
the hashtag ask a budget or as many of
them as i can
i also do have a moderator so right now
i am doing this live stream somebody is
moderating the live chat yeah and i have
um
moderators who actually look at their
comments also and they do whatever work
is required for that so i don't look
into all those things but i do look at
all the comments with the hashtag
because that's what i need to do to
answer your questions and i should
select the questions myself instead of
having them having somebody else select
that from me to select the questions for
me so that's what i do
sudesh says will you be ready to go to
mars if you get a chance
uh
if if our friend elon musk offers me a
ticket to mars i will be happy to go
with the with the condition that i
should be able to return to earth yeah i
i would love to go out into space i
would love to go to mars if i ever do
get the opportunity
um
yeah i mean i since i was a kid i always
was fascinated with space space travel
all that so if i ever get the
opportunity it would be the greatest
thing of course i don't mind investing
setting aside a couple of years to do
that
a one-way trip to mars takes about nine
months or so
in the right uh launch window so yeah i
don't mind doing that provided uh i'm
i'm guaranteed that i do come back to
earth so in that case i would certainly
be happy with that so my dear friend
elon if you listen if you're listening
i'm i'm up for it
all right all right all right so let's
take some questions from the live chat
shall we
live chat
why do i have a longer hair because i
like long hair i'm a lazy you know
when the pandemic started i stopped
stopped having a haircut and then then
it just continued but at least i do
shave
so yeah there's no real reason for it
it's just something that happened and
then i then i ran with it
okay what else do we have do we have any
other interesting questions
tell me about the napoleon napoleon
bonaparte was actually uh from
the island of uh what is it called
what is that island corsica corsica
he was his mother tongue was italian
but yes he so
within a span of 20 years he went from
complete obscurity
to becoming the emperor of france in
italy an incredibly meteoric rise
and of course he was a very ambitious
person maybe too ambitious for his own
good and long story one of the greatest
generals we have seen in in history
but he was too ambitious for his own
good and he eventually ended up
destroying himself and his nation with
him with himself i mean imagine trying
to invade russia in winter
he knew winter is coming and yet he
invaded russia he actually succeeded in
taking moscow
but it was a hollow victory because the
russians gave up moscow but only after
burning the whole city so they said okay
go ahead go ahead take up go and sit in
this burnt out city so napoleon spent a
month in burnt out moscow and then
eventually he had to retreat but not
before the
russian winter
destroyed his army terrible terrible
destruction anyhow that's a bit about
napoleon i mean
it's a very long story you know
when will india approximately become a
10 trillion dollar economy are we going
in the right direction the first step is
five trillion dollars i am hopeful that
by 2025 we will become a five trillion
dollar economy it is still a steep uh
path
it may not happen but i am hopeful that
we will reach there by 2025. so you
don't look so far ahead right now you
need to look you're going to see when
you're climbing a mountain you never
look at the peak you look right in front
of you where am i putting my foot next
next step next step you keep doing it
you keep doing it eventually you end up
at the top of the mountain so the next
step for india is the five trillion
dollar economy market we have done a
good job by
eclipsing the the british by by going
past the uk we are not the fire fifth
largest economy next step next stop is
five trillion dollars hopefully by 2025.
and
um maybe by 2030 at least by 2035 we
should be at the 10 trillion dollar mark
that's what i'm hopeful for it should be
very much possible
okay any other questions do we have any
other interesting comments
um
messi or ronaldo messi or ronaldo i
think both are great both are unique in
their own way and
maybe ronaldo is overall a better
performer maybe maybe i haven't followed
football much of late so
i don't know for sure but yeah both are
great
bobby says every sector needs to grow i
completely agree every sector needs to
grow you cannot you cannot focus on only
some things and neglect other things
everything every sector of the economy
and the nation needs to grow i
completely agree
uh where else are what else do we have
do we have something else interesting
let me take one or two more questions if
there is something
that
catches my eye
uh there was no need of picking question
of europeans eating mummies i was having
my dinners well it it uh piqued my
curiosity and i found it interesting so
why do you talk boring questions don't
watch
i think i take very interesting
questions
i have very good taste in questions
all right
uh
are you into fitness yes i'm into
fitness where am i boxing gloves
i like to box you know punching back
workouts my typical punching bag workout
is 5000 punches that's a whole lot of
punches i try to squeeze that into 60
minutes and i need to take care of my
fists because that's a very high volume
of punching and i also lift weights and
all that
yeah so
i i certainly am into fitness a huge fan
of fitness a huge fan of lifting weights
and all that love it
okay what else do we have
turkey is not going to sell drones to
india all right no problem we'll make
our own runes we don't need turkish
drones
how long is russia going to continue the
ukraine war
so the question is what is russia's
objective
russia's objective now by now it's been
so many months it started in february
right now i think it's becoming clear
that russia's objective was to
neutralize the threat of ukraine see
ukraine had the largest army in
continental europe
an army that is bigger than germany and
transport together
massive army
and they had all this aid coming in from
nato
so that was a
almost an existential threat for the
russians so russia's actual objective
seems
to have been
to completely neutralize this threat to
neutralize the ukrainian army and to
ensure that it is never a threat to
russia again
it was not really to capture the whole
of ukraine and all that which they have
not shown any inclination to do
so they have captured the regions that
are of interest to them the donbass
region the crimea region and slowly they
will take over the the black sea uh
region as well but the real objective is
to
ensure that ukraine is never a threat
again for them and they are succeeding
very well at that and they've already
captured more than a quarter of the
entire nation of ukraine which is which
is a huge nation isn't it
so that
and i think this
this entire uh campaign is going to
continue for the foreseeable future
russia is in no hurry it is classic
slow war
step by step and they are they are doing
well they have not even used the air
force which they are keeping reserve in
case it is needed for some other reason
so yeah that is the situation and that's
what we can surmise
from
how things have gone in the past
you know many months
okay my friends
we are at the end of today's session
thank you very much all of you for
making this a wonderful session great
questions
and let's keep doing this and maybe
something new next week perhaps let's
see all right
all right thank you very much everybody
have a good night good day wherever you
are take care and i will see you in the
next live stream until then bye